A Guide to the Virginia Dept. of Deaf and Hard of Hearing, Records, 1948-2002 (Bulk 1970-2002 )
Library of Virginia
Library of Virginia
Records of the Dept. of Deaf and Hard of Hearing, 1948-2002 (Bulk 1970-2002)
The Library of Virginia
41645
3.7 cu. ft. (3 cu. ft. boxes and 2 letter boxes)
Virginia Dept. of Deaf and Hard of Hearing
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
Transferred by Elaine Ziehl, Virginia Department of Deaf and Hard of Hearing, 1602 Rolling Hills Drive, Richmond, Virginia, 6 January 2005.
Historical Information
The Virginia Department for the Deaf and Hard of Hearing was established as a state agency under the Secretary of Human Resources by the 1972 General Assembly. Its predecesor ws the Council on the Deaf. The Department is advised by the nine member board (Advisory Board to the Department for Deaf and Hard of Hearing) appointed by the governor. Four members of the board should be representatives of deaf-oriented professions, four should be hearing-imparied citizens and one member should be a parent of a hearing-impaired child. The board is responsible for the approval of long-range programs and reviews budget request. The governor also appoints a director for the agency who is responsible for providing training and techical assistance to service providers and the general public about hearing impairmentm actung as an advocate for the deaf and hard of hearing, providing communications accessibility for hearing-imparied citizens through its Telecommunications Assistance Program, providing local and statewide outreach services and maintaining a register of hearing-impaired Virginians. This register is confidential and is used for needs assessment and research purposes. The Code of Virginia (63.1-85.1.1 et seq.) establishes the department as a communications bridge between those who are deaf or hard of hearing and hearing persons.
Scope and Content
This collection describes the genesis and growth of an angency with a specific mission, to provide aid and guidance for the deaf and hearing impaired individuals of the Commonwealth. The records include minutes, subject files and financial documentation of advisory board members, budgetary records and general correspondence.
Arrangement
This collection is arranged into the following series:
Series I. Minutes and Related Material, 1973-2000
Series II. Executive Orders and Memorandums, 1948-1998
Series III. Advisory Board Records, 1973-1994
Series IV. Financial and Conflict Disclosure Records, 1975-1998
Series V. Subject Files, 1985-2002
Series VI. Photographs, 1980-1990 circa
Contents List
- Series I. Minutes and Related Material, 1973-2000., Extent: 1.40 cu. ft. (Box 1-2)
  The Minutes and Related Material documents the activities of the Virginia Council of the Deaf and Hard of Hearing, the Virginia Department of the Deaf and Hard of Hearing and the Advisory Board to the department. The minutes provide the members or staff present, approval of previous minutes, old business, new business, guest in attendance and interpreters' present goals, suggestions and plans are highlighted in these records. There are minutes from later years that are signed and dated by the Chairman of the Advisory Board, Director of the Department and/or the Secretary. Statistical data concerning the cost of operations of the department are among the many topics covered. The data reflects the number of people helped and the many areas of opportunities for assistance. The creation of the Interpreter Service Program monitors and establishes guidelines and standard for interpreters and sets pay guidelines for salaries of interpreters. There is much discussion of the legislative initiatives undertaken by the department for the purposes of increasing funding for projects such as educational programs for the hearing impaired assisting them with parenting, job seeking and leadership skills. There is much documentation in the minutes on the development of Telecommunication Relay Services, a communication system that allows deaf people to receive written text phone messages through a TTY phone device. This series is arranged chronologically by date.
  - Board Minutes, Virginia Council for the Deaf, 1973-1974 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Board Minutes, Virginia Council for the Deaf, 1975-1977 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Board Minutes, Virginia Council for the Deaf, 1978-1980 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Board Minutes, Virginia Council for the Deaf, 1981-1982 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Board Minutes, Virginia Council for the Deaf, 1983-1984 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Board Minutes, Division for the Deaf, 1985 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Board Minutes, Department, 1986 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Board Minutes, Department and Advisory, 1987 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Board Minutes, Advisory Board, 1987 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Board Minutes, Advisory Board, 1988 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Board Minutes, Advisory Board, 1989 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Board Minutes, Advisory Board, 1990-1992 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Board Minutes, Advisory Board, 1993 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Board Minutes, Advisory Board, 1994 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Board Minutes, Advisory Board, 1995 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Board Minutes, Advisory Board, 1996 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Board Minutes, Advisory Board, 1997 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Board Minutes, Advisory Board, 1997 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Board Meeting Cassette Tapes, 1997 August 13 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Support Documentation, 1987-1997 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Organizational Chart, (Legal Folder), 1984 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Quarterly Fiscal Report, (Legal Folder), 1982-1986 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Board Minutes Advisory Board, 1998 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Board Minutes Advisory Board, 1999 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Board Minutes Advisory Board, 1999 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Board Minutes Advisory Board, 2000 (Box 2, Folder 4)
- Series II. Executive Orders and Memorandums, 1948-1998., Extent: .30 cu. ft. (Box 2)
  This series provides copies of Executive Orders and Memorandums created during the administrations of various Governors' from William Tuck to James Gilmore III covering many differing topics. Executive Orders are issued by the governor to accomplish specific goals and carry the full force of law. Executive Memorandums provides guidelines to state agencies and reflects the Governor's wishes (without the force of law) and usually expires upon the end of the Governor's terms.
  Governor Charles S. Robb created an extensive amount of Executive Orders and Memorandums that reflect the economic period of the early 1980's. There are Executive Orders concerning a state hiring freeze, guidelines controlling employment and the creation of the Governor's Economic Council. The Governor Robb's Executive Policy Memorandum 1-82 requires a review of all existing regulations and the drafting of future policy initiatives.
  Governor Gerald L. Balilies Executive Orders and Memorandums highlights continue budget and funding concerns with Executive Order 9 (86) requiring the creation of a commission on funding state programs and Executive Order 12 (86) creation of an advisory board on the economy.
  Governor Lawrence Douglas Wilder also has an extensive amount of Executive Orders and Memorandums during his administration. During the 1990's many states put pressure on companies doing business with South Africa (due to the country's apartheid policy) requiring companies to divest investments in South Africa. Governor Wilder's Executive Order number 8 (90) require the divestment in firms operating in South Africa.
  Governor James S. Gilmore III., instituted Executive Order 4 (98) which declared a state of emergency for Virginians suffering due to severe weather conditions, including a heavy snowstorm that resulted in floods and high wind damage for the Western portion of the state. This was among many orders issued by the Governor in 1998. Some of the orders approved by the Governor were in existence during previous administrations. There is a summary report entitled, "Executive Orders Currently in Effect as of July 1998". The records in this series is arranged chronologically by date and Executive Order and Memoradum number.
  - Index and Table of Contents, 1978 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Tuck, William, M., Governor, Order, 1948 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Holton, Linwood, Governor, Orders 13; 28, 1971-1972 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Godwin, Mills, E., Jr., Governor, Orders 15; 24; 28; 30, 1974-1976 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Godwin, Mills, E., Jr., Governor, Orders 31; 42; 44; 46; 47; 50; 51; 53; 54; 57-60, 1974-1977 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Dalton, John, N., Governor, Orders 1-18; Memos 1-78; 3-78; 4-78, 1978 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Dalton, John, N., Governor, Orders 21-35, 1979 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Dalton, John, N., Governor, Orders 37-43; Memos 1-78; 1-80, 1980 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Dalton, John, N., Governor, Orders 47-49; 51-54, 1981 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Robb, Charles, S., Governor, Orders 1-30; Memo 1-82, 1982 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Robb, Charles, S., Governor, Orders 32-40; Memo 2-83, 1983 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Robb, Charles, S., Governor, Orders 41-51, 1984 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Robb, Charles, S., Governor, Orders 54-56; Memo 1-85, 1985 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Baliles, Gerald, L., Governor, Orders 1-34; Memo 1-86, 1986 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Baliles, Gerald, L., Governor, Orders 35-36; Memo 4-87, 1987 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Baliles, Gerald, L., Governor, Orders 57-65, 1988 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Baliles, Gerald, L., Governor, Orders 66-81; Memos 1-89, 2-89, 3-89, 1-90, 1989-1990 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Wilder, Douglas, L., Governor, Orders 1-28; Memo 2-90, 1990 (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Wilder, Douglas, L., Governor, Orders 29-34, 41; Memo 1-91, 1991 (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Wilder, Douglas, L., Governor, Order 57; Memo 3-92, 1992 (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Wilder, Douglas, L., Governor, Memos 2-93; 5-93; 1-94, 1993-1994 (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - Allen, George, F., Governor, Orders 1,2,9, 12-15, 17, 20,21, 24, 27, 30-34, 36-38 Memos 3-94; 7-94; 8-94; 9-94, 1994 (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - Allen, George, F., Governor, Orders 39-44; 46, 48-51; 55-59; Memos 1-95; 2-95; 3-95; 4-95, 1995 (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - Allen, George, F., Governor, Orders 60-70; Memos 1-96; 2-96, 1996 (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - Gilmore, James, S., III., Orders 4-8; 11-26, 1997-1998 (Box 2, Folder 29)
- Series III. Advisory Board Records, 1973-2000., Extent: .30 cu. ft. (Box 2-3)
  The Advisory Board Records gives correspondence, memorandum and reports documenting the activities of the director and acting director for the Virginia Council for the Deaf. Directors of the department during the time period of these records are Lily P. Bess, Fred Yates Jr., Susan Walker-Buckland and Clayton Bowland. Board member records are also included in this series. There is discussion concerning the quality of education for deaf students. The records offer Position Papers describing legislative proposals supported by the council. There is information concerning budgetary plans and outlines for the department. There is documentation of efforts by the Council to inform their constituents and the public about resources available to members of the deaf community.
  There are correspondence reflecting the establishment of the teletype centers, designed to operate as a clearing house for messages received and given by the deaf community through TDD (Telecommunication Device for the Deaf) equipment to those without TDD devices. TDD devices are electronic equipment that provides text communication through telephone lines enabling the deaf to communicate.
  The Advisory Records gives parliamentary procedures for board members to follow when holding meetings and includes resumes, curriculum vita and application forms of individuals seeking appointment to the Advisory Board. This series is arranged chronologically by year.
  - Correspondence and Memorandum, 1973-1983 (Box 2, Folder 30)
  - Correspondence and Memorandum, 1974-1984 (Box 2, Folder 31)
  - Correspondence and Memorandum, 1981-1984 (Box 2, Folder 32)
  - Correspondence and Memorandum, (Legal Folder), 1983-1984 (Box 2, Folder 33)
  - Correspondence and Memorandum, 1984-1985 (Box 2, Folder 34)
  - Correspondence and Memorandum, 1986-1987 (Box 2, Folder 35)
  - Correspondence and Memorandum, 1987 (Box 2, Folder 36)
  - Correspondence and Memorandum, 1988 (Box 2, Folder 37)
  - Correspondence and Memorandum, 1989 (Box 2, Folder 38)
  - Correspondence and Memorandum, 1990-1991 (Box 2, Folder 39)
  - Correspondence and Memorandum, 1991-1992 (Box 2, Folder 40)
  - Correspondence and Memorandum, 1992-1993 (Box 2, Folder 41)
  - Correspondence and Memorandum, 1993-1994 (Box 2, Folder 42)
  - Correspondence and Memorandum, 1994-1995 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence and Memorandum, 1995-1996 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence and Memorandum, 1996-1997 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence and Memorandum, 1999-2000 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence and Memorandum, 2001 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Buckland, Susan, Walker, Director's Files, 1994-1995 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Cornett, Betty, L.,(Board Member), 2000 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Ebeling, Rebecca, (Board Member), 1999-2000 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Hutcheson, Leslie,(Staff Member), 2000 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Iqbal, Zarar, M.D.,(Board Member), 2000 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Patron, Rhonda, 1999-2000 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Schweiger, Leo, (Board Member), 1997 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Tabb, Barbara, (Board Member), 1999-2000 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Board Evaluation Information, 1999-2000 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Board Report; 2000 Survey of State Commissions, Divisions, and Councils Serving Deaf and Hard of Hearing People, 2000 (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Board Sample Information Packets, 2000 (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - Board Training Activities, 2000 (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - Board Training Manual: The Development, Organization, and Functioning of a Voluntary Board of Directors, 1982 (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - Parliamentary Procedures, 2000 (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - Recommendations to Governor for Board Appointments, 1983-1987 (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - Recommendations to Governor for Board Appointments, 1985-1986 (Box 3, Folder 21)
- Series IV. Financial and Conflict Disclosure Records, 1975-1998., Extent: .30 cu. ft. (Box 3)
  The Financial and Conflict Disclosure series provides memorandums and directives explaining the Virginia Conflict of Interest Act. This act requires board members to be forthcoming with personal financial interest information that might be considered as having a substantial affect concerning on decisions or actions board members make for the agency. There are samples of blank and completed disclosure statement forms. This series is arranged as received roughly chronolgically by year.
  - Conflict of Interest Statements, 1975-1989 (Box 3, Folder 22)
  - Conflict of Interest Statements, 1990-1993 (Box 3, Folder 23)
  - Conflict of Interest Statements, 1993-1994 (Box 3, Folder 24)
  - Conflict of Interest Statements, 1995-1996 (Box 3, Folder 25)
  - Conflict of Interest Statements, 1997-1998 (Box 3, Folder 26)
- Series V. Subject Files, 1985-2002., Extent: 1.39 cu. ft. (Box 3-5)
  This series features the Subject Files created during the tenures of various Director's of the Virginia Department of the Deaf and Hard of Hearing. The records provide information on the operation of the department. There are calendars chronicling the planned activities for the Director and Acting Director of the department. There are conference materials and studies on the future direction of the agency and the subsequent impact to the deaf community. The statewide conference "Beyond the Year 2000: Are You Ready?" featured keynote speakers from the agency and experts in the field of communication discussing future employment opportunities for the deaf and others interested in working in this hearing/communications field.
  There are request for information from the Governor's office, General Assembly or other state agencies are highlighted in the collection and shows the interaction between every aspect of state government. There is a draft report commissioned by the Virginia Department of Medical Assistance Services prepared by research associates from the Center for Public Policy Research The Thomas Jefferson Program in Public Policy at the College of William and Mary. The report is a comprehensive study of health care related Boards in the Commonwealth of Virginia and was undertaken as part of a request from the General Assembly Senate Joint Resolution 317, 1997. The General Assembly was attempting to reduce duplication of services and consolidation of missions of various boards. The Subject Files have correspondence from people seeking employment and the City of Richmond's Police Department requesting a "Best Practices Guide" offering instructions for working with the deaf community. There is communications with other states offering comparisons on their administration of deaf policies for their citizens along with request from scholars seeking statistical information for studies about the deaf community. This series is arranged alphabetically by subject.
  - Americans with Disabilities Act, undated (Box 3, Folder 27)
  - By-laws, 1985-1997 (Box 3, Folder 28)
  - Calendars, (Acting Directors'), 1996 (Box 3, Folder 29)
  - Calendars, (Directors'), 1996 (Box 3, Folder 30)
  - Calendars, (Directors'), 1997 (Box 3, Folder 31)
  - Calendars, (Weekly Planner), 1997-1998 (Box 3, Folder 32)
  - Communication Access Committee, 2000-2001 (Box 3, Folder 33)
  - Comprehensive Community and Facilities Master Plan, 1998 (Box 3, Folder 34)
  - Conference: Beyond the Year 2000: Are You Ready?, 1998 (Box 3, Folder 35)
  - Department of Aviation-Procedure for State Plane Use, 1999 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Department of Professional and Occupational Regulation-Biennial Report, 1996-1998 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Dickinson, Beverly, File, 1997-1998 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Director, Announcement of, 1997 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - General Correspondence, 1991-1994 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Interpreter-Position Description, 1997 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Listings-Directory of Contacts, 1995-1997 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Meetings; Speech to Speech, 2001 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Newspaper Ads-Recruit, 1997-1998 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Position Exemption Requests, 1987-1997 (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Program Report: Profile Virginia Dept for the Deaf and Hard of Hearing Mission, Programs and Issues, 1986 (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Secretary of the Commonwealth, 1999 (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - Secretary of Health and Human Resources, 1995-1997 (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - Senate Joint Resolution Study of Health Care Related Boards in Virginia, 1997 (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - Staff Meeting Minutes (Dept), Nov-Dec 2000 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Staff Meeting Minutes (Dept), Jan-June 2001 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Staff Meeting Minutes (Dept), Aug-Sept 2001 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Staff Meeting Minutes (Dept), Mar-June 2002 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Telecommunication Relay Services Proposal, 1990 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Town Hall Meetings, 1998 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Virginia Code Commission, 1997-1998 (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Virginia Employment Commission,1998 (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Virginia Quality Assurance Screening, 1996-1997 (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - Virginia School for the Deaf and Blind, 1986 (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - Washington Post, 1997 (Box 5, Folder 11)
  - Y2K-Year 2000, 1998 (Box 5, Folder 12)
- Series VI. Photographs, 1970-1990 circa., Extent: .01 cu. ft. (Box 5)
  This series has one contact sheet featuring board members of the Virginia Department for the Deaf and Hard of Hearing. An accompanying negative for the contact sheet is also a part of this series. This series is arranged as received.
  - Advisory Board Members for Department of Deaf and Hard of Hearing Contact Sheet and Negatives, 1970-1990 circa (Box 5, Folder 13)